Pāñchajanyam Trust proudly presents…
…Srī Vēdānta Dēsika’s…
…Ghaṇṭāvatāram…
…(Background Song) The pure soul who emerged on the holy day of Śrāvaṇam…
Some errors are possible due to the negligence
and paucity of skills of the actors.
But great hearts forgive them and appreciate the effort.
—Swāmi Dēsika (Yādavābhyudayam)
Raṅga…
[Kāñchipuram, a few years back]
Move … give way. Our Āchārya is coming … please give way…
Greetings, hope you are doing well.
Yes, good.
Āttigiri Aruḷāḷa … Prabhō … Vāsudēva … Namō Namaha.
Oy … who is standing in the way?
How would people go if you stand like this?
Swāmi—
He is an Āchārya. Please don’t say or do anything negative to him.
Mmm … He may be your Āchārya, but not mine.
I am in the exalted position of doing service to Perumāḷ.
Oh … This is boiling hot. Move.
Swāmi
… should the milk be so hot?
Can you not make it lukewarm before offering it to Varada?
Oy, you may be the Āchārya for your śiśyas. But not for me.
Keep your sermons for them.
My family has been serving for many generations; don’t teach me.
Sorry Swāmi. Please don’t say anything.
You are a great Āchārya, right? Why don’t you do this for Perumāḷ?
Here, take this. Go ahead.
Please wait. Priest, can you please bring that vessel?
Varada, I’m offering this milk at the right temperature for you to drink.
Please accept it.
Priest, please offer this to the Lord.
Yes, yes, offer it to the Lord.
My Lord, please have this milk; it won’t burn your lips.
Dear Vātsya Varada Guru, I’m overwhelmed by your love.
You gave me milk today just like my mothers,
… Kauśalya, Dēvakī and Yaṣōda.
In my Archai (idol) incarnation, you also become my mother.
O, King of all gods!
Swāmi, please forgive me.
Just like how a mother gives milk with a lot of love…
… should we also not celebrate Him in this idol form
with the same motherly affection?
After all, Varada is a God who speaks.
Of course, of course.
Since Varada has called you as His mother…
… we will also call you “Amma” from now on.
Varada…
Victory to Naḍādūr Ammāl. Victory to Naḍādūr Ammāḷ!
Welcome Rāmānuja! Welcome Vādi Hamsāmputāchārya!
Why address me with so much respect [when I am much smaller in stature]?
Why not? I am proud to call you that way.
Swans fly away on the sight of rain clouds.
Similarly, all the people who misinterpret Srī Bhaṣyakāra’s doctrines…
… fly away in fear when you enter the hall for a debate.
Calling you like this gives me great happiness.
Aha!
That’s why I’m addressing you as Vādi Hamsāmputāchārya!
It is my privilege.
It is not just me, but your grace and blessings are present…
…in abundance for my brother-in-law Anantasūri and sister Tōtārambā as well.
Oh, has Anantasūri come here?
Great pleasure.
Welcome Anantasūri.
Your father Puṇḍarīkakśa is a great Sōmayāji (one who does Vedic Sacrifices).
I’ve had the privilege of attending the many yajñas he has conducted.
You’ve been born in such a great lineage in Viśwāmitra clan
… and have married our daughter Tōtarāmbā.
Undoubtedly, you have the complete grace of Lord Varada.
I will pray to Him to give you a child soon.
May all good things come your way.
Tōtārāmbā? Tōtārāmbā.
Yes…
…I’ve been seeing you for some time now. You seem to be worried.
Yes Swāmi.
It’s been a while since we got married.
Still, we’re unable to beget a child.
Even Naḍādūr Ammāl blessed us the other day, right?
That’s true.
I have an idea.
I’ve been wanting to go to Tirumala for some time.
Shall we go on a pilgrimage to Tirumala?
Let us. It would be a pleasure.
Be careful my dear!
Greetings.
O Lord of the Holy Hills of Tivuveṅkaṭa!
We have come seeking your blessings. Please fulfil our wishes Gōvinda.
Tōtārambā, doesn’t the Lord look resplendent?
Yes Swāmi. My heart feels so full and happy now.
Srīnivāsa!
From where have you come, Swāmi?
We’re coming from Perumāḷ Kōil, Tūpul.
May the Lord’s blessings be with you.
Both of you will have a child soon.
You can stay at my humble dwelling.
That would be fine, thank you.
What is He thinking about standing all alone?
My Lord?
My Lord!
What’s with the deep thought?
Nothing, Dēvī.
My Lord!
Your “Nothing” has a million meanings in it.
I took many incarnations to establish Dharma (righteousness) in the world.
Later, I incarnated as many Āchāryas and gave the right Śāstras (doctrines) to the world.
Yes, Swāmi. What is there to think about it?
What shortcoming is there in your efforts Swāmi?
I understand now.
Due to Kalī’s might, adharma is prevalent everywhere.
To take people on the right path…
… there has not been a great Āchārya since Rāmānuja.
Is that not what you’re thinking?
Yes, Dēvī?
I can hear the bell in Vaikuṇṭha.
And I have an idea now.
Tell me Swāmi.
Let us make our Ghaṇtāzhwār (Sacred Bell) to incarnate on earth.
Earlier, a Brahmin boy called Kṛṣna did penance, remember?
My child, Kṛṣna!
We are happy with your penance.
Having got all the wealth in this birth…
… you shall be born as Vēdāntāchārya in the next birth.
You shall preach the path of complete surrender to the world…
…and you shall reach Us in Vaikuṇṭha.
Yes, my Lord.
You had also blessed him to be reborn as the Guru of Vēdāntic Doctrine.
Yes, he is the one.
He will reflect Me and will be an incarnation of My bell.
He will be born to Anantasūri and Tōtārāmbā.
He will ensure that our sampradāya (tradition) is celebrated again.
The world will know Our Grace through him.
It feels heartening to hear this Swāmi.
O Tirumaṅgāi of Kañchi!
He will also be the one to bring forth your greatness to the world.
Ok, come. Let’s bless Anantasūri and Tōtārāmbā.
Srīnivāsa … Srīnivāsa …
… Srīnivasa … Gōvinda!
Oh, what a beautiful dream!
What is it Tōtārambā?
Swāmi, I had a wonderful dream.
What was it?
I dreamt that Perumāḷ’s sacred bell was going into my stomach.
What is it?
It is all His grace.
What is he looking for?
I don’t understand……
…What are you searching for?
Can’t find the bell, Swāmi…
…How come?
How would I know? I just got here myself.
Search inside that garland. It could be there.
What is he doing there?
What happened?
Can’t find it anywhere.
Did a rat take it?
Or did they distribute it too like puḷiyōtarai (tamarind rice)?
It is so strange…
…Oh! Jīya Swāmi has come. Thank God.
Swāmi, Perumāḷ’s bell is missing—
Jīya!
My bell will be born as the son of Anantasūri and Tōtārambā.
You don’t have to ring the bell for Me during the Tiruvārādhana rituals.
She had a dream last night.
In that dream, perumāḷ’s Sacred Bell …
… went into her womb.
Lord Vēṅkaṭēśa is going to be born as their son.
Srīnivasa … Vēṅkaṭanātha … Gōvinda … Gōvinda ……
He is the pure soul who emerged from Tūpul on the holy day Śrāvaṇam star.
He is the leader of the Holy Vēdas.
He is the incarnation of the divine bell of Lord of Tirumala.
He is the Ghaṇṭāvatāram of Srī Vēṅkaṭēśa.
He is a form of Guru Srī Rāmānuja.
He emerged due to the grace of Magizhmāran, the leader of Tamil Vēdas.
He is the pure soul who emerged from Tūpul.
He is the light of knowledge in Kali Yuga.
He emerged to make the Lord of the Karigiri Hills (Lord Varada) happy.
He is the Dēsika who explained the greatness of Lord Srīranganātha’s Holy Feet.
Hail the one who conquered the fake philosophies and established Srī Rāmānuja’s Viśiṣṭhādvaita unequivocally.
Hail the one who warmed the heart of the ever-famous Srīperumbudūr-born (Rāmānujāchārya).
Hail the one who pleased the Lotus Dame (and received the title ‘Sarva-tantra Swatantra’)
Hail the one who always had in his heart the meaning of Tirumaṅgāi Āzhwār’s (six) Prabandhas…
Hail the one who clearly enunciated the rich and authentic Tamil Vēdas known as ‘Divya Prabandha’.
Hail the one who was born as the great Bell of the Lord of the Seven Hills.
Hail the one who handed us the Doctrine of Prapatti—the great means—through masterpieces like ‘Srīmad Rahasya-Traya Sāram’.
Hail Vēṅkaṭanātha of Tūpul who is a Master of excellent Tamil.
Vēṅkaṭa, Tiruvēṅkaṭa!
Both of you look like a divine couple.
Today is my son’s puṇyāvachanam and naming ceremony.
Kindly come in and bless him.
He is the dear son of Anantasūri and Tōtārāmbā.
He has the blessings of the Nithyasūrīs (Eternal Souls) like Ananta and Garuḍa…
He defeated non-believers and established Tamil Vēdas.
He ensured that the sound of Praṇava echoes in every part of the world.
He is the pure soul who emerged from Tūpul on the holy day of the Śrāvaṇam star.
Who is it? Rāghavāchārya?
Yes.
Please come, please come Rāghavāchārya. What is the matter?
Where is little Vēṅkaṭanātha?
He hasn’t been coming to learn his lessons for a week now.
What! Hasn’t been coming for a week?
Yes. Is he in good health?
No, he is fine. Let me see.
Vēṅkaṭanātha!
Come, my child!
Greetings, Teacher.
Namaste!
Why have you not gone to the school for a week, my child?
Father! He is teaching me the same lessons again and again.
How can I complete my studies if he doesn’t teach me new lessons?
Is that so? Vēdas are Śrutis (those that must be heard).
They must be repeated to gain mastery.
I am blessed to retain your teachings when you teach just once to me.
How surprising! Vēṅkaṭanātha, can I test you?
Yes, please!
Tell me the first Pañchati in the first Praśna of the fourth canto?
[Sanskṛt verse chanting]
That should do.
Anantasūri! Vēṅkaṭanātha does not need to come to Santai sessions any more.
Why?
I will come here to teach him.
Excellent, thank you very much.
I shall leave now.
Greetings.
I listened to this conversation.
I will teach my nephew Tarka, Vyākaraṇa, Mīmāmsa, Kāvya and Nāṭaka.
Tomorrow is Prauṣṭhapada śravaṇa.
It is the Tīrthavārī (Holy Immersion Festival) of our Lord Vēṅkaṭeswara.
Vijayadaśami.
Our Vēṅkaṭanātha’s birthday.
Let’s start our Śāstram lessons from tomorrow…
Excellent!
I shall take your leave.
Uncle?
Yes, my child?
I’ll also come along.
I am going to Naḍādūr Ammāl’s Kālakśepa (Traditional Learning Lessons) now.
It will take a long time.
Can you stay there that long?
I promise to be quiet there.
I will not disturb the Kālakśepa.
Very well. Let’s go…
Greetings.
Uncle?
Yes, my child.
What is the difference between Kālakśepa and Upanyāsa (discourse)?
Upanyāsas are works that help common men…
… understand epics such as the Rāmāyaṇa and the Mahābhārata.
In Kālakśepam, āchāryas explain the texts…
… of our traditions and religious systems to their students.
Do you see the difference now?
Yes, I do.
Uncle, I will be right back.
What happened, my child?
My dhoti has become dirty.
I will change and come with a Daṇḍa (baton) to seek the His Holiness’ blessings.
All right.
Oh, this boy looks so radiant!
I hope you are well.
Yes, Your Holiness.
The child looks so divine!
Isn’t he your nephew, Vēṅkaṭanātha?
Yes, he is!
He looks like a re-incarnation of Swāmi Rāmānuja.
Shall we being with our Kālakśepa?
Where did we leave it before?
Aha! The boy looks so radiant!
This is Sudarśana Sūri.
We forgot the stopping point upon seeing the child’s radiance.
Perhaps my presence disturbed the gathering.
May I say where you stopped when I came in?
Are you sure?
Go ahead.
The first Adhikāraṇam in the first Adhyāya of Srī Bhāṣyam.
This is where you stopped when I came in.
Wonderful!
Vēṅkaṭanātha, come here.
Go, my child.
Greetings.
[Sanskṛt verse chanting]
No more worries.
He shall be the protector of our Srī Bhāṣyakāra’s tradition.
Unbelievable, Rāmānuja Swāmi!
Yes, Your Holiness.
I’m too old to complete Kālakśepam for this young boy.
So, you must teach him everything.
This is also the wish of Varada.
So it shall be.
Greetings.
Tirumaṅgā, can we please leave now?
See how beautiful Perumāḷ looks.
Wait, Mother!
Are you coming? I’m leaving now.
Welcome, how are you?
Look at her.
She is engrossed in Perumāḷ, temples, tanks and thoughts about Him all the time.
How am I to get her married?
She makes me anxious.
What do you think of our nephew Vēṅkaṭanātha?
You mean Tōtārambā’s son?
Who in entire Kāñchipuram who doesn’t know him?
He is believed that he is the incarnation of Tirumala Perumāḷ’s Holy Bell.
Will you give your Tirumaṅgā in marriage to my nephew Vēṅkaṭanātha?
Wouldn’t that be a blessing!
Tirumaṅgā!
Yes, Mother?
Here comes his Āchārya himself.
What are you talking about?
All good things. Do you see this child?
Of course, Tirumaṅgā. I know her well. A good girl.
I was thinking if we could get her married to Vēṅkaṭanātha—
Of course, what could be better than that?
Varada, your wish. Good news. Let it happen.
Greetings.
Please bless Tirumaṅgā and Vēṅkaṭanātha.
Tirumaṅgā, I have taught Garuḍa Mantra to Vēṅkaṭanāthan.
He will be going to Tiruvāhīndrapuram to meditate on it.
[Swāmi Dēsika offers his salutations to the Srī Vaiṣṇava guru lineage starting from Devādinātha and his consort Kamalā…
Viśwaksēna, Swāmi Nammāzhwār, Swāmi Nāthamuni, Uyyakoṇḍār,
Manakkal Nambi, Ālavandār, Rāmānuja, to his guru Appuḷḷār,
Prostrations to all of them.]
—Ślōkam 2, Dēvanāyaka Pañchāśat by Swāmi Dēsika…
…Oh Supreme Master of the assembly of Dēvas! Everyone of your limbs is filled with Saundarya and Lāvaṇya. Hence, it is not easy to describe the incomparable beauty of your divine body.
Jewels and weapons gain lustre through His association and Your consorts don’t even wink for fear of missing the divine experience.
As for me, the flood of beauty associated with your Holy Presence overwhelms me…
…my eyes enjoy this unparalleled beauty of yours without satiety.
—Verse 14, Dēvanāyaka Pañchaśat by Swāmi Dēsika.
We practice the chanting of the Garuḍa Mantra with Praṇava, the main import of all the Vēdanta.
This is Brahman, the embodiment of bliss absolute, after doing anganyāsa, karaṇyāsa and digbandha, and then start the japa.
The word Pakśi or the reverse of it with Praṇava either in the beginning or after the word, along with the name of the wife of Agni.
This is the mantra which has Garuḍa as its invocatory deity.
Vynathēya. Vihākēśwara! Pakśirāja! Vēdaswarūpa. Humble greetings to you!
Vēṅkaṭanātha, being pleased with your sincere penance,
… I shall teach you the great Hayagrīva mantra.
You will attain siddhi on performing ārādhana to this Yōga Hayagrīva idol.
In His beautiful, lotus-soft four hands, Lord Hayagrīva sports the Sudarśana, Pāñchajanyam, Jnāna-Mudra and a Book.
He is seated on a freshly-blossomed White Lotus and reminds the worshippers of the whitest-white fragment of a freshly cleaved Sphaṭikam.
His lustre never ever fades. There is no limit to His blemish-less glories.
May this Lord of Vidyā shower on me His nectarine, white and cool rays! May He reside and preside over my heart in this manner!
—Ślōka 32 from Hayagrīva Stotra by Swāmi Dēsika.
Hayagrīva! Gōvinda! Vāgīśa! Namō Namaha!
Vēṅkaṭanātha! May you drink the nectar of knowledge from me…
… and excel in all arts.
The Halāhala sounds in the form of neighings emanating from the divine throat of Srī Hayagrīva, the Horse-faced Lord, are the aggregate of Sāma Vēda Mantras, The word for word meanings of the Rigvēda and the abode of Yajurvēda Mantram.
These HalāHala nādhams are the destroyers of all obstacles to true Jnyanam about Chethana-Achethana-Isvara tathvams.
These Halāhala sounds are like the movement of the waves from the ocean of true knowledge (Jnānam).
May these holy sounds chase away the inner darkness arising from the uproar of debaters whose minds are driven by their own pride, arrogance and lack of knowledge.
I’m worried as my father Appuḷḷār’s health is in a bad shape.
Please inform Veṅkanathāchārya immediately.
Of course, right away!
Rāmānuja … my Āchārya …
Uncle, I have come.
My child!
Good you came.
Vēṅkaṭanātha … come.
Careful, careful.
I lost my parents at a young age.
You raised me as a father and mother. Now, your health—
My son, I have something to give to you. That … that … Bring that.
Rāmānuja, my Āchārya! My Rāmānuja!
These are the Holy Sandals of Swāmi Rāmānuja. This is your wealth from now on…
Swāmi! Swāmi! I have no one … no one…
The size of the uñchavritti vessel is becoming bigger by the day.
What are you saying?
Oy, I’m not talking about you. Look there.
What is the use of learning so much and living according to our Śāstras?
If you have to go for alms for just one bowl of rice.
Well said.
These scholars show off their austerity.
They take alms in the fear that their hard-earned wealth…
…would get exhausted soon. This is Kaliyuga!
Kaliyuga.
Careful, he might curse us.
I am sure he is well-versed in matras and tantras.
Curse? Me?
Others may believe when he says he has the…
… grace of Garuḍa and Hayagrīva. Not me.
My salutations to both of you.
Who are you my boy?
My name is Rāmāñju. My marriage has been fixed.
Is that so?
Yes, sir.
Excellent. Why have you come here?
My father-in-law expects me to earn a lot of money.
So, I have come to earn.
A most perfect goal in life. Excellent.
Hey boy. Shall I tell you an easy way to make money?
Please tell me!
Do you see him there?
Yes?
Go to his house. He is a rich man.
He has sacks of gold in his house.
Really? And money?
Go ask him and he will give you lots of money.
You will find gold coins scattered on the floor of his house.
Will I really get lots of money if I go to his place?
Of course you will.
Will he give some to me?
Fantastic.
You must both come for my wedding.
Definitely. We will be there.
Now you run to his house.
Swāmi?
What is it, Maṅga?
I found something shiny in your uñchavritti pot today.
Is it? Show me?
Oh! I refused the money that Taṇika Mādhavāchārya gave.
That is probably why he put these gold coins in the pot today without my knowing.
All right.
Maṅga, these are poisonous germs.
They are unfit to be offered as part of Ārādhana.
Here you go, it is clean.
Go and prepare food for offering to God.
All right, Swāmi.
Ah, just like the men said, there are coins lying around!
Greetings!
Who are you, child?
Sir, my marriage has been fixed.
I came here because people said I will get a lot of money if I came to you.
That aside, did you eat?
I drank a lot of water from the Anantasaras Puṣkariṇī.
(The tank of Varada’s temple.)
What?!
Maṅga? A boy has come. Could you serve him some food?
Yes, Swāmi.
Sir, what about money?
Eat first.
Those in this world who wish to start yogic activities…
… with an eager mind approach you to seek wealth…
… for dharmic activities. Give them their desire of…
… wealth and allow it to grow.
—Verse 16, Srī Stuti by Vēdānta Dēsika.
O Mother! Mahālakśmi! Perundēvī! Jagadjananī! Please bless this child.
Shower of gold coins! What a wonder!
Swāmi, there is no match for your greatness.
This is all for you. Take them, child.
Peraruḷāḷa permanently resides in the hills of Hastigiri.
He emerged from the Aśwamēdha Yajna of Brahma and looked like a fire with a bluish hue.
His beauty is further accentuated by the presence of His consort who appears like…
… a golden creeper embracing the Karpaga tree.
—Verse 1, Srī Varadarāja Pañchaśat.
Thus, Brahma carried out the Aśwamēdha Yajna for destruction of his…
… karmas that led him earlier to think that insignificant worldly pleasures…
… are great and lasting. At the conclusion of the Aśwamēdha with…
… great bhakti for the Lord, Brahma Dēva performed the Vapā hōma.
Immediately thereafter, the supreme radiance of the Lord arose from the middle…
… of the Yajna Kuṇḍa shining like thousands of suns. It was like the rise of…
… a golden mountain surrounded by Puṇya Kōṭi Vimāna, which made the regular sun…
… look like the lamp lit on a bright day.
—Verse 15 from Atithigiri Mahātmyam by Swāmi Dēsika.
[Verse 3 from Āṇḍāḷ’s Tiruppāvai Pāsuram]
Stop it! Stop it!
Why should we stop?
In place of the Vēdas that have no beginning or end…
…we will never accept singing songs in the baseless Tamil!
This Adhyāyana Utsava has been happening since the times of Kaliya.
Nothing doing!
Other than Sanskṛt, the commoner’s languages such as Tamil…
…should not be heard inside the temple premises.
The low-caste-born Āzhwārs should not worshipped inside the temple.
Why should we stop? We will go ahead with the Adhyāyana Utsava.
In that case, win a debate on this topic with us and continue your Utsava.
Otherwise, we’ll never allow singing of Tamil songs in any temple.
Oh, all right. Let us debate.
Yes, let’s see.
We must immediately inform Sudharśana Sūrī of Srīraṅgam…
… that the Adhyāyana Utsava has been stopped.
Come, let us go.
Hey, Raṅganātha!
What kind of a test is this?
Adhyāyana Utsava has been stopped!
I have grown old now.
I do not have the energy for a debate any more.
What is it that you are doing?
Who else do I have other than you, Raṅga?
Tell me what is in your mind, Raṅganātha!
What a wonder! The flowers from His chest have fallen on the bell.
This is His order. He has chosen Vēṅkaṭanātha for this debate.
Srīnivasa! Go to Kāñchipuram, inform Vēṅkaṭanātha about this…
… and bring him with you. Quick. Go on.
As you wish, Swāmi.
This temple is the home of the sweetest nectar.
This was the gift given by Brahma to the king of Ayōdhyā.
This was the temple prayed to by the invincible Rāma.
This temple was given by Rāma to Vibhīṣaṇa.
This temple gives all the combined benefits.
This is the temple with its Vimāna shaped as the Praṇava.
This is the temple that resolves all problems.
This is the temple of Srīraṅgam.
Raṅga, why is he not here yet?
This delay—
Welcome, welcome. I was waiting for you.
What would you like me to do?
They are stopping Perumāḷ’s Adhyāyana Utsava.
You’re an incarnation of Rāmānuja.
My āchārya Nadādūr Ammāḷ’s blessings are with you.
You must defeat them in the debate.
Salutations.
Here comes Tūpul Vēṅkaṭanāthāchārya.
My salutations to all of you.
May victory be yours!
What radiance!
So, are you the Vēṅkaṭanātha?
Isn’t the ākāram a little too shrunken? [Pun on appearance]
Paṇḍitji, can ākāram shrink? [Pun, again.]
It is surprising to see that you don’t have this basic literary knowledge!
That apart, why did you try to stop the Adhyāyana Utsava…
… that has been happening since ancient times?
At home, you can talk in whatever language you want.
But a temple is a divine place, where lowly languages are not allowed.
What is low? Ṛśis like Agastya have developed this language.
These sacred Tamil Hymns are ancient and have no equivalent to them.
Do you know how foolish it is to call this a lowly language?
The Perumāḷ and Āzhwārs love it when we sing in our mother tongue.
Can we call this a lowly language?
We are Vaidikas; those who follow the vedic Śastras.
So, we will never accept any language other than Sanskṛt.
O scholars! Sanskṛt is indeed a great language.
But why don’t you try to experience the bliss that comes with listening to our Āzhwār’s songs?
Doesn’t the Sanskṛt Vēda recitation group follows the Perumāḷ during utsavas?
True. But doesn’t also the Perumāḷ follow the Divya Prabandha
recitation group during the same utsavas?
Doesn’t this show the greatness of Tamil as well? Think about it.
Paṇḍits, we are those who have mastered the Vēdas in both Tamil and Sanskṛt.
Tamil and Sanskṛt are equally important to us.
How can you choose between the two of your eyes?
Kaliya started this utsava and Nāthamuni continued…
… it with fervour. It was firmly established by…
…Swāmi Rāmānuja. Since this has been happening for…
… such a long time, it is foolishness to stop it now.
Even if we agree, not all Āzhwārs (Tamil saints) are brahmins!
Is it not a sin to worship their idols inside the temple?
What is sin? Our Perumāḷ has accepted them with love.
Don’t you know the story of Thiruppān Āzhwār who…
… was carried by sage Lōka Sāraṅga on his shoulders?
Raṅganātha is waiting to listen to Āzhwār’s pasurams. Don’t stop it.
But—
But, what? This is also the Vedic path.
It is our pride to chant Prabandhas (Tamil Hymns) in temples!
Why limit it to here?
We will sing our Āzhwār’s Pallāndu pallāndu even in Vaikuṇṭha!
From now on, there should be no hindrance to Raṅganātha’s utsava!
Open the Paramapadam Gate. Let Raṅganātha’s procession begin!
Since you won the debate today, you will henceforth…
… be called Vēdantāchārya. This is Raṅganātha’s order.
My privilege!
Victory be to Swāmi Vedāntāchārya!
[Periyāzhwār Tirumozhi, Pāsuram 1-2-1]
Hey Maṅgaḷam? Why are you awfully quiet?
Watch your step!
I’m seeing everything. Tell me.
What is there to say?
Even Maṅga doesn’t say anything.
Oh yes, she doesn’t express anything.
That’s why she doesn’t talk.
That is right.
Doesn’t wear any jewellery…
… hides all of it, and…
… walks around as though she has nothing…
… They say, her husband is a great scholar.
He must have many students.
Would there be dearth of money?
She must be saving a lot of money.
She should have garlands of pearls…
… rubies and other precious stones.
Maybe she doesn’t wear them because…
… we’ll be jealous of it all.
You are right.
Maṅga, these people are talking ill of you.
Why aren’t you saying anything?
Leave them. Let them talk.
Kamalā, do you know something?
No, what is it?
When her husband recites the Mahālakśmi stōtra,
… apparently, gold coins pour down.
Everyone around gets them; takes them home.
My husband is my biggest treasure.
I don’t wish for any other wealth.
I haven’t desired anything either.
Did her husband really give all that money to that boy?
What do you say of that?
Dispassion.
Did you know?
Apparently, many kings met with him.
And this man never bothered about all that!
Apparently, he threw away all the gold coins…
… that he had gleaned.
(Mockingly) Some life he lives!
Maṅga…
… Your married life is a disaster.
Stop hurting her feelings.
Her life is much better than all ours.
We are only speaking the facts, aren’t we?
’course!
Very bad of you all.
Whatever, Kamalā.
They will never be as smart as you.
Isn’t it the wife’s responsibility to advise her husband?
If not for themselves,
… mustn’t they save for their children?
What children?
She seems barren.
That’s enough!
Watch your words.
Paṅkajam, what they’re saying is right.
But there are things beyond the reach of their minds.
Those that live in the vanity of material wealth and those
that discard material and hold in their heart the only dweller
of the Kāñchi Puṇyakōṭi Vimānam are beyond comparison.
Children are part of the family life.
But is losing yourself in lust a way to live?
My husband’s work are my jewellery.
Srī Bhāṣya Sampradāyam born out of…
… Varada’s six words is our wealth…
… His students are our children.
The life we lead is Varada’s blessing.
Let’s go.
Yes, let us.
Greetings.
It has been long since I came to Srīraṅgam.
I wish to visit the other Divyadeśams.
I came here seeking your permission.
Travel well.
[Tirumala]
Dayā Dēvī, I am the emperor of sins.
You are the Empress presiding over the Lord’s Ananta Kalyāṇa Guṇas.
Oh, Empress, invade my kingdom of sins,
… conquer my kingdom and place me at the feet of the Lord at Tirumala.
—Verse 30, Dayā Sātakam by Swāmi Dēsika
Oh Holy Mother.
The ruler of all worlds.
The one who emerged from the lotus.
The divine grace of Vṛṣagirinātha!
The merciful one.
I seek your blessings.
Here comes Mahāchārya of Vijayanagara…
… Srī Srī Vidyāraṇya Swāmi.
[Kāñchipuram]
Vēṅkaṭanātha!
Yes, Mādhava!
We’ve played for too long.
And you’re tired?
Yes.
How come you’re not tired?
What are you thinking about?
In some days,
… we will finish school and separate.
Would you forget me?
How can I ever forget you?
Is that all our friendship is?
Anyway, what are you going to do after schooling?
I’m going to learn the Śāstras from my uncle.
Spread Yatirāja’s tradition all around.
Learn the Divya Prabandhas (Tamil hymns) with their meanings.
What about you?
I want to be a royal Paṇḍit.
And spread the teachings of the Śāstras throughout the world.
Don’t you have such ambitions?
A king is like a mustard living a transient life in this vast universe.
I will not be subservient to him.
Even if hunger hits me like a volcano under the ocean,
… I shall quench it with anything from a nearby pond.
But I will never serve a king.
Your Holiness.
You’ve been watching the Vaiṣṇava for some time now.
Do you know him?
Yes.
He is a great scholar.
Very patient.
An ocean of knowledge.
He’s the Vēṅkaṭanāthāchārya of Tūppuḷ.
A childhood friend.
Dispassionate about material pleasures since childhood.
He still hasn’t changed.
He’s become a teacher to the world.
And I remain a royal guru.
I am but a saint.
But him—
… He’s your childhood friend.
I’m sure he still has affection for you.
Yes, I’m sure he has.
And I’m proud of it.
But he wouldn’t like to see me at this time.
And I don’t want to make it awkward for him.
Come, let’s go.
[Kāñchipuram]
[Recitation of Verse 10 from the Dēsika Prabandham, Tiruchchinnamalai]
Varada!
Your beauty is beyond expression!
I am so blessed to be able to pray to you!
How wonderful!
Varada has awarded the Swāmi who sang the…
…Tiruchchinnamālai with one of his two holy symbols.
Going forward, Varada would have one symbol,
… while the other will be with our Swāmi.
Greetings, Swāmi!
[Messenger from Vijayanagara]
Who are you, child?
I have come from the court of the king of Vijayanagara.
Is my childhood friend, Vidyāraṇya, well?
He is well.
He has sent a note for you.
Is that so? Do read it out.
[Vidyāraṇya Swāmi addresses Vēṅkaṭanātha Swāmi]
The kings of the Vijayanagara empire, known for…
… their efforts in spreading the Sanātana Dharma…
…wish to make you the Chief Scholar of…
… their empire and honour you with gold coins.
I hereby request you to honour the kings’ wishes…
… and join the Royal Court immediately.
Is that all?
That is all.
Even if hunger burns my stomach like a volcano…
… I shall quench it with water in local ponds…
… rivers, why, even potholes and fields,
… but never, ever, serve a king.
My ancestors did not leave me anything.
And I am like this.
But…
… my grandfather, the Brahmadēva…
… has left me great treasure.
Would you like to know what, child?
Yes, of course, tell me!
So…
… do you know the tall hill called Attigirī,
… on the banks of Anantasaras Puṣkariṇī?
Standing atop the hill is Kaṇṇa…
… guarding everything and everyone.
There He stands, granting everyone’s wishes.
Is all this greater than that, to me?
Oh, welcome, welcome, Puṇḍarīkākśa!
Welcome.
Greetings.
It has been long since I saw my Āchārya’s daughter and son-in-law.
What brings you so far?
Here is the idol of Hayagrīva, given to Bhāṣyaka by Saraswatī.
Yes, of course!
Worshipped by Tirukkurugai Pirān Piḷḷān.
The Almighty has instructed me to hand over the idol to you.
That is a privilege!
Hayagrīva!
God of voice!
Swāmi Rāmānuja, wrote a brilliant explanation for Vyāsa’s Brahmasūtras…
… and presented them in the presence of Dēvī Śārada, in Kaśmir.
The Goddess, immensely pleased with the work,
… held it to her head and praised it.
She called it Srībhāṣyam, and…
… called our Swāmi, The Bhāṣyakāra.
Not only that, she gifted him the idol of her guru, Hayagrīva.
Child…
… In what way is what I will get in the court better than this?
Puṇḍarīkākśa, come let us go in.
What exactly are you looking for?
Today is special.
How so?
Is it someone’s death anniversary?
Yes.
Ah, so a good day for you!
Don’t get me started.
Why, what happened?
This Vēṅkaṭanāthāchārya—
You mean the one whom everyone calls Dēsika?
Who else?
The śrāddham is in his house.
Why would you go to the pauper’s house?
Why would I go to his house?
Then?
What are you looking at, then?
I’ve stopped every priest from going to his place.
Let us see what the “great paṇḍit” does.
Some great thing you did.
Let us see what happens.
Oh, I can hear mantras being chanted in the house!
Is the śrāddham happening?
Did someone go in or what?
How can that be?
I’ve been watching like a vulture since morning.
Hold on, let me see.
[Mantras chanting]
Looks like someone is coming.
Ah, what is this?!
I see just footsteps!
There is nobody!
Are these pitṛdēvatas?
Deities from three of the Divyadēśas graced my father’s śrāddham.
Swāmi, Swāmi! Save us!
What happened?
Please save us!
Our children are dying!
Our cattle and children are all dying in Tirupputkuzhī.
Only you can save us.
You must save us.
Let us not go there.
We would get the plague as well.
Nārāyaṇa, how insensitive of you!
We will be in danger by trying to save them?
So what?
This is the path Rāmānuja showed.
Only he who helps those in need can be a true Vaiṣṇava.
My dear ones, don’t worry.
You shall get the blessings of Sudarśana (Tiruvāzhī Āzhvār).
Victory be to Sudarśana.
Dear Chakra.
Cure these children with your grace.
Give these children good health.
The fear that has gripped the village should go away.
Praise be to Sudarśana.
Ah, what wonder!
Swāmi, you have saved our clan with your grace.
Sudarśana’s grace and your skills have saved our village.
Quick, quick!
Let me see if someone is coming.
Wait a moment.
Everyone is praising the man as Vēdānta Dēsika and talking about him.
Hearing his name irritates me.
I have hung my footwear now.
Let us see what he does.
Looks like someone is coming. Let us leave.
What is this?
Footwear hang like a tōraṇa!
Perhaps Vaiṣṇavas have sent their blessings.
In this world, some walk the path of good deeds.
Some others seek knowledge.
But,
… Some like me, worship the pādukās of Vaiṣṇavas.
Isn’t his a blessing!
Āchārya!
Oh no, this is not right. Forgive us!
Swāmi, please forgive us!
You are the epitome of sainthood.
Please accept us as your students.
Please accept us as your students, Swāmi.
[Song praising Varada]
[Ślōkas chanting]
Kumāravarada?
What book is this?
There once happened a discussion on the phrase, tattvamasi between…
… Vidyāraṇya, an Āchārya of Advaita, and…
… Akśobhya muni, an Āchārya of Dvaita.
This is a collection of it.
They have asked for a judgement.
Based on the arguments, Akśobhya muni has won the debate.
But isn’t Vidyāraṇya your childhood friend?
Yes, he is.
But here, facts presented in the argument matter; one must be objective.
Kumāravarada, you were born to me after years of childlessness.
That is my privilege.
Our ancestors have always walked the path of dispassion.
Dispassion, determination and walking on the…
… path shown by our scriptures go hand in hand.
I wear these studs because of their austere penance.
Even your mother wears only those ornaments…
… that she wore during our wedding.
To us, dispassion and following the divine path are important.
Do you understand?
I do.
Oy, Vaiṣṇava!
Stop.
How come you are trying to ignore me?
Who are you?
Why should I particularly notice you?
Don’t you know who I am?
I am an expert in black magic.
I control all the demons.
Everyone in this village should obey me going forward.
Otherwise……
…Do you see our Āchārya there?
Vēdānta Dēsika.
His grace rules this land.
Your tantras won’t work here.
Go show your tricks elsewhere.
Such disdain!
Let me see who it is.
Let me see.
Swāmi.
Yes, Hastēśa?
I have a request.
Hastēśa, you are my favourite disciple.
So far, you have not asked anything of me.
Do not hesitate to ask; what do you wish?
This materialistic life does not interest me.
I want renunciation, and I need your blessings for it.
Your determination is exemplary.
You have the blessings of the Almighty and Rāmānuja.
May your wish be fulfilled.
Come, let us go.
What radiance! Let me go closer.
Hmm, something seems to stop me.
I must do more penance to be able to act against him.
Swāmi, what happened?
Something is not right.
What?!
Nṛsimha!
With the fierce rituals I plan to perform today…
… the Vaiṣṇava shall die of a bloated stomach.
Let me preserve some of the soil from his footsteps.
I shall fill his stomach with this water.
[Dark chants]
Today, Hastīśa expressed his desire to renounce…
… worldly pleasures and become a sanyāsī.
And I consented.
Here, I fill his stomach with this water.
This is the end of Vēṅkaṭanātha!
Swāmi, what happened?!
Why is he in pain?
It is all due to the tantras.
Some black magician has sinned against me.
Black magician? Who?
Ah, my stomach is bloating. Nṛsimha!
Āchārya!
Don’t worry.
Nṛsimha will shower His grace.
[Song in praise of Nṛsimha]
Ah, what happened? Why am I losing my powers?
Nṛsimha’s grace is always there for us.
Srī Lakśmī Nṛsimha!
Ah, wonderful! Water is flowing from the pillar!
Unbelievable!
I see something.
Eh, what is that?
Ah, a lion!
Ah, my body is burning!
It’s Nṛsimha! Ah!
Someone save me!
Swāmi, please forgive me!
Please save me!
You are a lion among poets and debater, who has the grace of Nṛsimha.
I tried to harm you.
Please forgive me.
Māyāvī, never used ill-gotten powers to harm good people.
You will be well.
Swāmi?
You are seen as an expert composer and a great poet.
They say you are an expert in all art forms.
Can you make a well using these crooked bricks for me?
These bricks?
Yes.
Sure.
Swāmi!
You are great!
You constructed such a beautiful well with those crooked bricks!
You truly are a master of all crafts.
Therefore…
… The importance of understanding the essence…
… is more important than mere recitation.
Do you understand?
Swāmi.
Oy, Swāmi!
Who is this man?
Are you the master of all arts?
And who would you be?
Can you tame my snake?
Let us see?
Why is this snake charmer coming in my way?
Hmm, so be it.
Vainatēya will protect me.
Let me meditate on Garuḍa Panchākśarī and draw the line.
Snakes cannot cross this.
If they do, Garuḍa will protect me.
Vainatēya!
O, king of birds!
[Vēdam Ennum Kūṭil (song on Garuḍa)]
Here comes my Pakśirāja; the king of birds!
Son of Vinatā!
Rushing to protect me!
Look at that!
Here he takes away the snake, the Śaṅkasuta!
Oh, my snake!
Swāmi, please forgive me!
I blindly erred!
Gather yourself together.
Don’t make such a mistake again. Get up.
Swāmi, please forgive me!
I offended you not knowing who you are.
My snake is my livelihood. Please return it to me.
Forgive me.
Vainatēya, please return his snake to him.
Here comes your snake.
See what my Garuḍa can do?
Here, take him and go.
Thank you!
Be well. Don’t harm others. Stay blessed.
O, Dēvanāyaka, please permit me to visit more Divyadēśas.
[Pon Viḷaintha Koḷattūr]
Maṅga?
I see a village.
Just a little further.
Let us stay the night here.
Yes, Swāmi.
Rest for a bit.
Walk slowly and carefully.
We are exhausted.
Let us stay here and continue the journey tomorrow.
This way.
Careful.
Varada!
Sit.
O, Lord.
Swāmi…
Swāmi?
Yes, Maṅga?
Over the last three days, you merely offered pure water to…
… the Lord and having drunk only that, you have tired.
If you go on with this, your health will deteriorate.
This body would perish one day anyway.
Should we really worry about it?
My lord Hayagrīva has been starving for three days.
Why, even you are suffering.
Water is all I can offer during this…
… journey, to Him the ruler of the worlds.
Don’t worry about it.
Sleep.
What do I hear?
Some travellers. Hmm.
Oh, a horse! My grains!
Oy, Vaiṣṇava!
Get up! You are sleeping while your horse does this?
Go, tie it.
What, my horse?
Of course your horse.
Maṅga,
… this is Hayagrīva’s game.
Sir, can I get some milk, please?
I am asking you to tie your horse and…
… you are asking for milk in the midnight?
Already the harvest hasn’t been good for years.
There’s been drought.
Now this?
Please don’t be angry.
All right, give me a moment.
Keep this with you.
Here you go.
Thank you!
What is he going to do?
O horse-faced epitome of knowledge!
Have you come to bless me?
Here, drink this milk.
And bless this farmer.
Maṅga, let’s go.
Sir, thank you.
Ah, what in the world is this?!
There is gold along the horse’s path!
What wonder is this?
O, great man!
You are a holy incarnation!
[Srīraṅgam]
She is the eternal abode of all good things…
… the epitome of compassion…
… the garland on the crown of the Vēdas…
… the lofty wealth of the Lord…
… the boon-granting Kāmadhēnu.
May she reside in my heart.
[Verse 24 of Srī Stuti by Swāmi Dēsika]
Attention.
Please make way for Kavitārkika Simha.
So he is the Kavitārkika Simha?
Yes, he is.
The lion (king) among poets is the Kavitārkika Simha.
Don’t you know about his Sanskṛt and Tamil hymns?
He has written so many Stōtras in Sanskṛt…
…and Prabandhas in Tamil.
Look closely.
[Swāmi Vēdānta Dēsikan’s Taniyan]
Our elders have said this, haven’t you heard?
I haven’t come to argue with you.
If he is a great poet…
… and has won many awards…
… will he be able to compete with me?
What an absurd question!
Vāsudēva, that is enough.
Control yourself. Never condescend a devotee.
Why the silence?
Worried that your (lack of) skills will be revealed?
O, scholar…
… I have the grace of Lord Hayagrīva.
Debates never intimidate me.
But…
… I don’t support conflict among Vaiṣṇavas.
I have no qualms in accepting…
… that you are a poet par excellence.
Excuse me, I shall leave now.
Oy Swāmi!
Don’t try to slither away like this.
You must engage in debate with me.
I can write a thousand verses about the Lord’s holy feet.
Likewise, you must also write.
Let the Vaiṣṇavas decide next morning…
… who is the finest poet.
Why is he being so aggressive?
What is my dear friend Pāduka Dēvī thinking about?
Let me see what it is.
Dēvī?
What is with the deep thought?
Oh, nothing at all.
Right, your nothing does not mean a million things.
Do you know our Vēṅkaṭanātha?
Yes, what about him?
Well, you know he has sung songs about the many consorts of the Lord.
Right.
Of all the consorts he has sung about, he has never…
… even sung once about me, the Pādukādēvī.
One needs to be fortunate, perhaps.
That is what you are thinking about?
Perhaps Vēṅkaṭanātha is waiting for the right opportunity.
What opportunity? He just lost a golden one.
Did you not see it yourself, Dayādēvī?
He did not take that poet’s challenge to write a…
… thousand verses about the holy feet of the Lord.
You have a point.
This world should know of the prowess of our child, Vēṅkaṭanātha.
There, he is walking into the sanctum now!
Instruct him to write a thousand verses on Pādukā Dēvī tonight.
He would never say no to his mother.
You are right. So it shall be.
Ah, why isn’t the Satāri coming off his head!
May be it is Pādukā Dēvī’s game.
You must compose a thousand verses on Pādukā Dēvī by tonight.
This is Pādukā Dēvī’s order.
As She wishes.
Oh, what a wonder!
[Rangā, Rangā!]
Vēṅkaṭanātha, as per Pādukā Dēvī’s orders…
… you must compose a thousand verses by tonight.
Salutations to the Divine Sandals of Srīranganātha!
Would Vēṅkaṭanāthāchārya have completed composing the verses?
Nah. No.
He couldn’t have.
Only I shall.
O Holy Feet, O Vēdas, O sound!
Argh, where are these boys?
Kēśava!
Mādhava!
Where on earth are you?
Call that Ananta.
I asked you to go check on Vēṅkaṭanāthāchārya; what he is up to.
Raṅga!
Are you asleep?
I don’t understand what to do.
I don’t get the rhyme, nor do I see my disciples.
What do I do, Raṅga!
No, no. I shall win.
Nobody else would.
I shall finish composing a thousand verses by tonight.
O Holy Feet, O Vēdas, O sound!
I need Vainatēya’s blessings to complete…
… writing a thousand verses by tonight.
[Dēsika starts composing the verses, the Pādukā Sahasram]
Where is Swāmi?
Here comes the Swāmi.
Be victorious, Vēṅkaṭanātha!
Vāsudēva, please submit the work.
Salutations to Srīranganātha’s Holy Sandals.
Please recite the Pādukā Sahasram now.
Great men bear on their heads, with a great relish, the Pādukā of Srī Raṅganātha.
For this reason, they shine gloriously, the dust from their feet being potent enough to…
… grant protection (and salvation) to all the worlds.
I pay my homage to that great pioneer, Bharata…
… who was the first example for proclaiming the greatness…
… of the Pādukā of Srī Rama in this world.
(My homage is also due to Srī Nāthamunī…
… who was to Srī Nammāzhvār, as Bharata was to the Rāghava Pāduka.
And Nāthamunī—indeed Raṅganāthamunī—propagated Āzhvār’s work…
… by singing with tāḷa and abhinaya…
… that is with Bhāva, Rāga, and Tāḷa…
… which is what the Bharatamuni did for the fine art of dance).
Oh Pāduka Dēvī! I pay homage to that sage Nammazhvar…
… who also bears your name (Satāri, being absorbed in Raṅganātha’s feet.
I do this at the time of beginning your Stōtra. For it was he who “saw and…
… delivered” the Vēda called Thiruvoymozhi…
… which is only another form of the original Vēda and…
… whose verses and words emit the fragrance…
… of the Vakula flowers (dear to the Āzhvār).
I am going to sing the praise of the Pādukās of Lord Raṅganātha…
… which were first sung of by Sage Vālmīki and others…
… being emboldened by the fact that these Pādukās make no distinction…
… between the low and the high…
… they being pleased to sit on my lowly head as well as…
… on the highly-revered Upaniṣads, impartially.
[Continues with the Pādukā Sahasram]
O Master, Vedic scholar from Tūppuḷ, you are peerless!
I lost myself to arrogance and tried to compete with you.
I stand defeated; I was unable to write a thousand verses in a night.
I could write only six hundred.
Please pardon my arrogance.
O great poet, Raṅganātha and Pādukādēvī had…
… decided to make us compose a great work of divine poetry.
There is no winner or loser here.
Swāmi Dēsika has written many granthas.
May we get to know at least one…
… to be liberated from this world.
How true is all that our elders told us!
By order! By order! Swāmi Dēsika is arriving.
[Recitation of Verse 1008 from the Pādukā Sahasram by Swāmi Dēsika]
Swāmi?
Yes, Maṅga?
It is going to be the twelfth in a couple of days—
Okay, so?
No, typically, after bath I recite…
… all the four thousand hymns while cooking…
… before you come.
But it won’t be possible when…
… the twelfth finishes before dawn.
What do I do?
Good question.
Swāmi, I have a request as well.
You too? What is it, Rājagōpāla?
Please explain to us the essence of the Divya Prabandhas.
All right. I will mention the Āzhwārs’ days of birth…
… the stars, places and the count of the Prabandhas…
… in a work called Prabandha Sāram.
So that those who recite the essence get the…
… same benefits as reciting all the Prabandhas.
Maṅga, go and start your work.
Swamy Dēsikan records precisely for posterity…
… the authentic division of the 4000 sacred collect:
Toṇḍaraḍippoḍi (55 Pāsurams); Pāṇar (10); Tirumaṅgāi (1253)…
… the salvation-granting pāsurams of Amudanār on Srī Bhāṣyakāra’s…
… sacred feet (108); Mudal Āzhwār (300 in total with 100…
… each for Poigai, Bhūtam and Pēy); the luminous Tirumazhisai (216)…
… The Pāsurams of Swāmy Nammāzhwār…
… which are the essence of Vēdam (1296 housed in his four Prabhandhams)…
… the generous Madhura Kavi known for his Āchārya Bhakti (10)…
… King Kulaśēkhara (105); Periyāzhwār (473) and Āndāl…
… who is an incarnation of the Bhūmi Dēvī (173).
All of these add up to 4000 Pāsurams…
… that are the means to our upliftment.
Watch your step. Careful.
Swāmi Desika is here.
O great man!
Please forgive me.
Who … who are you?
Who are you?
Ah, aren’t you Kandāḍai Lakśmaṇāchārya?
Why has your health deteriorated so much?
All because of a sin I committed against you unknowingly.
When you were in Srīraṅgam, I came your way.
Engrossed in holy scriptures, you did not notice me.
My disciple forcefully brought you to me.
I didn’t know about this at the time.
Upset by the incident, you left Srīraṅgam…
… and came to Satyamangalam.
But a student’s actions affect the guru, and here I am in this state.
What is this?!
Please get up.
Swāmi, the water from your feet is the cure for my illness.
Srīman Nārāyaṇa!
[Recitation single-verse praise for Swāmi Desika]
Swāmi, please also grant us a boon to beget a child.
Swāmi, Swāmi! A great calamity has befallen us!
Dēvarāja, why are you in panic?
Calm down.
How do I even begin, Swāmi?
What happened?
I don’t understand anything, Dēvarāja.
The Turkish invaders are destroying Srīraṅgam, Swāmi!
Ah, it is indeed horrible!
They are destroying everything they see.
The Turkish army has come until Kaṇṇūr!
Raṅga! Raṅga!
Ambarīśa, did you hear what Dēvarāja said?
I’m unable to decide what to do!
Their main aim is to destroy Raṅganātha’s temple!
What dangerous game is this?
Srīraṅgam is in danger!
Raṅga, should you test us like this?
Ambarīśa!
First of all, ring the big bell and announce the situation.
Ask all our people to remain alert and careful.
Call all our palanquin bearers.
Ring the bell and announce the impending danger.
Dēvarāja.
It’s time to act swiftly.
We mustn’t waste time.
Guard the main deity and the idol we use for procession.
We must guard all of Raṅga’s jewels and vessels.
Yes, yes.
Priest, please get started.
O Lord Raṅga!
Oh, such misfortune has befallen Srīraṅgam.
Great men are even giving up their lives to save Srīraṅgam.
I am not fortunate enough.
What service can this lowly dancer do for you, Raṅganātha?
Yes. Yes, yes, that is the right thing to do.
I shall go right away to the Sultan’s quarters.
I shall entice him with my performance and stall the attackers.
By then they can save Raṅga’s idol.
This would be my service to Raṅganātha.
I shall do this even at the cost of my life.
Swāmi.
Swāmi!
Who are you, girl? What happened?
This is dancer Padminī, the one who lights the lamps for Raṅganātha.
I went to the Sultan’s quarters and mesmerised him with my dance and song.
He too lost himself.
To stall him, I consumed liquor with the same mouth that
I drank Raṅganātha’s pristine holy water with.
And I fed him poison-filled liquor with my own hands.
His army is now like a headless chicken.
Please use this opportunity and take away our Lord.
I have a request.
Would Raṅga accept this lowly sinner, Swāmi?
Would you pray for me, Swāmi?
The lord will certainly accept you, child.
Lord Srī Raṅganātha, please accept this pure soul.
She is a holy woman.
Please perform all the final rites befitting a Vaiṣṇava.
Vēṅkaṭanātha!
A big responsibility awaits you.
Yes, Swāmi.
Yes, indeed. We successfully saved the Utsava idol.
Having built this stone wall, I am going to follow Him.
Vēṅkaṭanātha!
I swear on Raṅganātha. You must not follow Him.
Swāmi, what are you saying?
You are like Hanumān;
… the root of this tradition.
Just like how Jāmawant said that if Hanumān were safe, Rāma’s army would be safe,
if you are alive, Srīraṅgam will regain its glory.
Vēṅkaṭanātha, I have another request.
Command, Swāmi.
This is the explanation for Srībhaṣyam, as…
… learnt during Naḍādūr Ammāḷ’s Kālakśepa.
I have compiled it in the form of a book.
I give this to you for safekeeping.
Go through its contents and explain the same to other students through Kālakśepa.
I am going to follow Raṅganātha.
I don’t know if I would ever see you again.
Both my sons are too young.
I hand them over to you.
Show them the right path.
Be their guru and guide them.
Raṅga!
Oh, they have come close!
Swāmi is in danger.
I must distract them somehow.
Raṅga!
Oh Lord, the Sultan’s army have wreaked havoc here!
Corpses everywhere.
Look, there is some movement there!
Who is there?
Janārdhana, what happened?
Where is Swāmi?
Janārdhana!
Tell us, where is Swāmi?
I don’t understand. Where?
I don’t understand what he is saying!
Corpses and streams of blood everywhere.
We hear howls of dogs and wolves in place of holy sounds.
Vultures and crows are hovering around.
I can hear someone coming.
Boys, hold your breath and stay still like
a corpse among these corpses.
Have no fear, I am right here.
Oh, how do I find Swāmi among these corpses?
I feel scared.
Would we find him alive?
Don’t say such things, Srīhari.
Ah, I see some movement there!
It’s our Swāmi!
Come quickly!
Oh, is that you?
I feared it was the Sultan’s army.
These are Sudarśana Sūrī’s sons.
Oh…
Why is all this happening?
Children?
Get up slowly.
Janārdhana jumped off a tree to distract the army in an attempt to save me.
Raṅga…
We must somehow reach Satyākālam.
Careful.
[On the way to Satyākālam]
Oh, I cannot find Swāmi!
What could have happened?
Even I am worried, Kaustubha.
Mother Tirumaṅgā and Kumāravarada reached here safely.
But we have heard nothing about Swāmi for months.
No news from Srīraṅgam has been good.
All right, let us all go into the woods in groups and look for Swāmi.
Yes, let us.
Whom do I see there? Swāmi? Our Swāmi?
Swāmi!
That is him all right!
Is this Satyākālam?
Yes, it is!
Srī Rāma?
Yes, Swāmi?
Take the children first.
[Satyākālam]
Greetings.
Ha, here is our Pēraruḷāḷa Jīya. He is doing well,
… establishing the principles of Swāmi Rāmānuja.
Pēraruḷāḷa, you shall be called Brahma-tantra Svatantra going foward.
Swāmi.
I have a request.
I need your permission to learn Bhagavad Viṣayam from Kumāravarada through Kālakśepa.
Beautiful. Today is the day of incarnation of Selvapiḷḷai Tirunārāyaṇār.
Hasta nakśatra of Avani.
Today is the day the followers of Sāmavēda perform their Upākarma.
An apt day to begin the Kālakśēpa of Bhagavad Viṣayam,
… which is the essence of Sāma Vēda.
Tirukkurugai Pirān Piḷḷān has given an explanation for Nammāzhvār’s…
… Bhagavad Viṣayam through a work called Tiruvārāyira Paḍī.
I have written an explanation for that called 74,000 Paḍi.
Start your Kālakśēpam along with it.
Swāmi, I have another request.
I would like to offer a one-verse praise (Taniyan) for recitation during Bhagavad Viṣaya Kālakśēpa.
I worship the Vēṅkaṭanātha, who is endowed with the auspices and glories,
who was a receptacle of mercy of his Āchārya Srī Rāmānuja,
who was adorned with jewels of wisdom and detachment.
Excellent!
Srīmān Vēṅkaṭanāthāryaḥ explains the greatness of our esoteric works,
… while Rāmānuja Dayāpātram is blessed with love by our Selvapiḷḷai.
Swāmi, I have yet another request.
I would like to present another one-verse praise, this one for Kumāravarada.
I take refuge at the sacred feet of Kumāra Varadārya,
who was born in the Viśwāmitra clan
and existed on this earth as the flag of victory of Srī Rāmānuja Darśanam.
Wonderful!
[Satyākālam]
Kunnattūr Ayya?
Yes, Swāmi.
Kōmanḍūrappa?
Pēraruḷāḷa?
Yes, Swāmi.
Kumāravarada?
This explanation on Srībhāṣyam is called Śrutaprakāśika.
Please teach this to your able students as well.
Commemorating the completion of Srībhāṣya Kālakśēpa twenty-seven times,
… here is another work called Tatvaṭeeka.
Our greetings to Śrīmat Nigamānta Mahādesika.
[Señji]
Greetings to Gōpanārya, the king of Señji.
Welcome, scholar!
I called you because—
What is it, O king?
I have been getting a dream the past few days.
I want to understand it.
Of course, tell me.
An unknown force pushes me into an old, dilapidated room.
It is quite dark.
I often get this dream.
But as soon as I go in, I see a wonderful radiance.
I am unable to understand what it is.
I would like to know what it means.
I feel you get this dream due to divine grace.
The explanations that we give are based on
the celestial positions and movements.
But we cannot understand divine intervention.
Only those who have the complete grace of the Lord
can explain these interventions.
I believe that you would get an explanation for this if you meet
… Vēṅkaṭanātha, also known as the Vēdānta Dēsika.
The Vēdānta Dēsika?
I sure have heard about him.
But I haven’t been able to move closely with him.
Would he lend me his ear?
I have heard that he hates kings and the royals.
He has never hated noble and just kings like you.
Is that so?
He does not come to royal chambers because of his displeasure
… towards materialism. Otherwise, he always blesses
… the noble deeds of kings.
Oh!
Srīraṅgam has lost its lustre because of the invasion by the Sultan.
The Raṅganātha is not there anymore either.
I heard that the Swāmi has moved from Srīraṅgam to
a place called Satyākālam in Karṇātaka.
Let us go meet him there.
Of course.
Please arrange for my meeting with him.
As you wish, O king!
[On the banks of Kāvērī, Satyākālam]
My wish is going to be fulfilled.
I am going to meet the great man today.
O, Raṅganātha, the Bauddhas, the Chārvakas today propagate their fault-ridden mantras
and are set to detroy your pristine Vaidika Maṭha.
The Turks and the Greeks appear like special agents of the Kali Puruṣa
causing grievous injuries to all who follow your path.
The land is experiencing fear due to the activities of these groups.
The fear grows further and further.
Your five weapons are powerful in destroying our enemies.
They protect the assembly of the sages.
Please use these weapons and chase away the fear enveloping this land.
Swāmi?
I am Gōpanārya, greetings.
That is enough, O king.
Why, Swāmi?
It is our privilege to be blessed by great people like you.
May you be victorious.
Thank you.
The paṇḍit informed me about your arrival.
O king, there are waves of anxiety in my mind as well.
Do you see thses…
… many, many idols of the gods that have taken refuge
… under trees and in caves? They are hiding.
Many temples that speak volumes of our art and divinity
have been plundered and are dilapidated now.
Great men like Piḷḷai Ulagārya, Sudarśana Sūrī and others have
… sacrificed their lives to save Lord Raṅganātha from the invaders.
Sacrifices don’t go in vain, Swāmi.
That is true.
But does that mean we should give up on our efforts?
Raṅganātha oders you—
Always waiting.
You must immediately bring Raṅganātha’s utsava idol
from Tirumala to Srīraṅgam.
Bring  all our warriors together.
Our Bhārata army should get to work right away.
Raṅganātha should emerge victorious!
We must hear echoes of victory everywhere,
… to Raṅganātha, to Sanātana Dharma,
… to Bhārata Deśha, our nation!
I give you all the benefits of my penance of reciting
… Abhīṭistava on the banks of Kāvērī, all these years.
Let the army get ready.
Victory to Raṅganātha! Victory to the Sanātana Dharma!
Victory be to Raṅganātha! Victory be to Raṅganātha!
[The Pōrāṭṭam song]
Fight, fight; fight to bring back our treasure.
Fight, fight; fight to revive Srīraṅgam.
It is time for Srīraṅgam to return to its glory.
It is time for the Vaikuṇṭha on earth to shine with its lustre.
Raṅga, Raṅga! Kāvērī Raṅga!
Raṅga, Raṅga! Kastūri Raṅga!
Raṅga, Raṅga! Parimaḷa Raṅga!
Raṅga, Raṅga! Srī Raṅga!
[Recitation of Verse 54 from Dēsika Prabandham (Paramadha Bhangam)]
O Dēvādirāja! Varada! Please protect the temples of all the holy places.
Swāmi!
Ah, what?!
I come bearing great news!
Is that so?
Gōpanārya has brought back our Raṅga
to Srīraṅgam to consecrate Him!
He has requested you to come right away to Srīraṅgam.
Kumāravarada, that is fantastic news!
My penance of so many days in Karṇātaka has borne fruits.
Yes, Swāmi.
Long live Gōpanārya, who brought Raṅganātha’s idol
from Tirumala to Señjī and then to Srīraṅgam.
We are going to Srīraṅgam to pray to Raṅganātha!
Such a blessing!
[Srīraṅgam]
Anybody in there? May I come in?
I’m very much here. Please do come in.
Are you the Vēdānta Dēsika?
The master of all arts?
But sculpting is a unique art form. Greater, more refined than others.
Not your cup of tea.
You won the Māyāvi with some mantras.
Fooled the villagers by eradicating the plague using your tantras.
You dug the well because you know Vāstu Śāstra.
But sculpting is a different beast.
Not something you can play tricks with.
So, you want me to compete with you in sculpting.
Yes.
All right, how do you want me to go about it?
The world says you are an expert in all 64 art forms.
If that is the case, create your own sculpture
… on a pedestal I give you.
We shall grade your talent based on it.
All right, please bring the pedestal.
Let me bring it.
This is the pedestal.
Let’s see; let’s test your skill.
Oh, he has made a realistic sculpture of himself
… on the pedestal that I gave him!
He is indeed prodigal.
But … I must find a flaw.
Ah!
Something on the right cheek seems amiss.
Let me scrape it a little with the knife.
A little better now.
Oh, your cheek is bleeding!
Swāmi, I only corrected the idol; why are you hurt?
This work of yours oozes life.
A highly exemplary piece of work.
I disrespected you with my arrogance.
Please forgive me.
[Srīraṅgam]
Just as Srīranganātha blessed Rāmanuja to live happily in Srīraṅgam
… we have also lived in bliss here.
Now my heart yearns to worship the Para-Vāsudēva.
Swāmi!
This is the Srīmad Rahasya Trayasāram.
This is the compilation of all the meanings learned from my
Āchārya and uncle, Appuḷār, or Vāti Hamsāmputāchārya.
This contains the meanings of several important aspects of our tradition.
Do spread this.
Jīya?
Henceforth, you would pray to this idol of Lakśmī Hayagrīva,
which was worshipped by Rāmānuja.
Kumāra Varada, this is our family treasure, the idol of Varada.
Your responsibility from now on.
Swāmi…
Kumāravarada … Jīya…
I am leaving for His holy abode.
There. Para-Vāsudēva is calling me.
The Nityasūrīs (Eternal Souls) are welcoming me,
the servant of His Holy Sandals.
Before that, let me take leave from the Perumāḷ residing at Tirumala.
Srī Raṅganātha…
Srī Vēṅkaṭēśa…
Srī Varadarāja…
Chellapiḷḷāi…
Allow me to leave.
[Song continues.]
Can Virajā match the Gaṅgā, Kāvērī or Vēgavatī in holiness?
Do you wish to enter the Vaikuṇṭham leaving behind
Tirumala, Srīraṅgam or Kāñchi?
Is it fair that you go to Vaikuṇṭham
leaving us deities yearning for you?
Vēṅkaṭanātha, forget Vaikuṇṭham and stay here on earth.
Please let me leave, O gods.
I want to go to Vaikuṇṭham, please let me go.
Kumāravarada, bring my Āchārya’s sandals.
Āchārya, Āchārya!
[Recitation of Appuḷḷār’s Taniyan]
Kumāravarada, Jīya, my blessings to you both.
[Verse 19 from Piḷḷāi Antādi]
[Subtitles: Sriranjani, Lavanya Rathnam and Ram Iyer]